<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Max Wolpert</title>
    <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Max Wolpert</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://mxwolpert.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Max Wolpert</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My work centers around processing at the sentence level. How do human parsers use competing sources of information to make sense of structure? How can we use diverse languages and language experiences to know what pieces of processing architecture are universal and what parts are shaped by experience? Do two or more languages occupying the same brain have shared or separate neural and cognitive representations?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adjective placement</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/adjective-placement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/adjective-placement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Relevant Publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Zhang H, Baum S, Steinhauer K, &lt;strong&gt;soon to be submitted&lt;/strong&gt; | Native and non-native parsing of adjective placement – an ERP study of Mandarin and English sentence processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most languages have the distinct word class of &lt;em&gt;adjective&lt;/em&gt; to modify nouns. How adjectives are arranged and modified within a sentence, however, varies among languages. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/applin/amu028&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Steinhauer (2014)&lt;/a&gt; found that violations of adjective-noun order in English elicit biphasic N400-P600 ERP responses. Importantly, advanced learners of English showed a similar pattern to their native counterparts, suggesting these structures are processed by a similar mechanism in both native and non-native English speakers. This native-like processing by non-native English speakers was present whether their first language had adjective-noun order (i.e., Mandarin) or noun-adjective order (i.e., French).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although native and non-native English speakers have been shown to have the same ERP response to adjective placement violations, it is not trivial whether this finding should extend to Mandarin adjective placement. Although they typically precede the nouns they modify, Mandarin adjectives have different properties from English, and may frequently occur in predicate position without an intervening copula. For example, it is possible to say both 等&lt;u&gt;绿灯&lt;/u&gt;了 &amp;ldquo;wait &lt;u&gt;green light&lt;/u&gt;&amp;rdquo; and  等&lt;u&gt;灯绿&lt;/u&gt;了 &amp;ldquo;wait &lt;u&gt;light green&lt;/u&gt;.&amp;rdquo; This variety in adjective placement can communicate subtle differences in meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested processing of Mandarin adjective-noun pairs in both native and non-native speakers. We constructed sentences such that the structure licensed only adjective-noun order and not noun-adjective order (e.g., 父亲最近想看新书了 &amp;ldquo;father recently wants to read new books&amp;rdquo;). For native speakers, we found the same N400-P600 pattern as previously reported for English, but with an additional N400 effect on the adjective in the correct word order. A possible explanation for this additional effect is a difference in the lexical nature of adjective-noun pairs between Mandarin and English. For non-native speakers, the incorrect adjective placement elicited only an N400 effect with no subsequent P600, a pattern that is consistent with relatively low second language proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside these group-level results, we found more insight by considering individual differences in N400 and P600 amplitudes. Both native and non-native participants showed a range of responses, from N400-dominant, to biphasic, to P600-dominant. With this response range, there still was not a correlation between any behavioral measure and ERP amplitude. These results add more nuance to existing discussion on N400-P600 effects in individual differences (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2014.02.002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tanner &amp;amp; Van Hell, 2014&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0229169&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fromont, Steinhauer, &amp;amp; Royle, 2020&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we used single-morpheme adjectives that can be paired with nouns without the particle 的 DE. These structure are considered to be undergoing a process of lexicalization and so may be qualitatively different from more typical adjective-DE-noun structures, especially when considering sentence processing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Argument structure</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/argument-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/argument-structure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Relevant Publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Ao J, Zhang H, Baum S, Steinhauer K, &lt;strong&gt;soon to be submitted&lt;/strong&gt; | The child the apple eats – processing of argument structure in Mandarin verb-final sentences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between verbs and their arguments are the foundation of sentence structure, and languages vary extensively in how these relations are expressed. English, for instance, relies almost entirely on word order to communicate agent and patient roles, and word order will generally &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; over other cues for interpretation in the case of ambiguity or competition with other cues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can test cue competition by using strange sentences like &amp;ldquo;The child the apples eats.&amp;rdquo; In this sentence, the verb &amp;ldquo;eats&amp;rdquo; is inflected for 3rd-person singular and semantic knowledge contends that apples cannot eat children. However, despite the cues of verb inflection and semantic knowledge, most English speakers interpret this sentence to mean that &amp;ldquo;apples&amp;rdquo; is the noun doing the eating, merely by virtue of directly preceding the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is your own interpretation of this strange sentence? If you speak a language other than English, you may be informed by cue weighting parameters of your other language. For instance, Mandarin allows both subject-object-verb and object-subject-verb word orders, as well as lacking inflection for subject-verb agreement. Accordingly, semantic knowledge and context drive Mandarin sentence comprehension, so Mandarin speakers often opt for the semantically appropriate agent of the verb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To study the fundamentals of argument structure processing, we had Mandarin monolinguals read sentences with a variety of grammatical and semantic manipulations (word order, presence of coverb, agent animacy, reversibility of the semantic event) while we recorded their EEG activity. We found that there is a language-specific profile of cue weighting that is more nuanced than a simple linear ranking, and even within a language there is individual variability in sentence comprehension strategies. EEG data showed that comprehenders likely do not wait until the verb to make argument structure decisions, and sentences whose grammar violates semantic knowledge elicit a brainwave pattern consistent with models that predict crosslinguistic differences in core processing mechanisms for sentence comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bilingual speech segmentation</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/bilingual-speech-segmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/bilingual-speech-segmentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Relevant Publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gilbert A, Lee J, Coulter K, &lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Kousaie S, Gracco V, Klein D, Titone D, Phillips N, Baum S, 2021 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.705668&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spoken Word Segmentation in First and Second Language: When ERP and Behavioral Measures Diverge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gilbert A, &lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Saito H, Kousaie S, Itzhak I, Baum S, 2019 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1121/1.5134781&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Adaptive and selective production of syllable duration and fundamental frequency as word segmentation cues by French-English bilinguals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the words on this page, there are not discrete boundaries between words and phrases in natural speech. To properly segment and parse sentences, listeners use a combination of top-down (e.g., knowledge of words) and bottom-up (e.g., prosodic cues) information as signals for dividing speech into comprehensible components. Speakers must also consider this information when producing utterances to make sure their listeners understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if speech segmentation were not already a difficult enough task, the acoustic cues for signalling boundaries also vary among languages! French, for instance, uses a large pitch contrast and lengthening to signal word and phrase offsets, while English relies more on lengthening and subtle differences in lexical stress. These crosslinguistic differences can lead to difficulty for second language learners to produce and comprehend appropriate segmentation cues. According to some accounts, the prosodic cues used for segmentation are perceptually wired in the brain in early life and resistant to modification by later life experience. In this way, whatever an individual&amp;rsquo;s native language is will drive their automatic segmentation strategies in whatever language they learn. Others support the idea that the brain can adapt to use appropriate non-native segmentation cues in a second language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our own data suggest that experience and language dominance may indeed be more important than nativeness. When we extend consideration to brain data as well, the picture becomes even more nuanced. EEG data further show that the brain can be sensitive to segmentation cues even when an individual cannot demonstrate this sensitivity behaviorally.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interlocutor identity</title>
      <link>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/interlocutor-identity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mxwolpert.github.io/projects/interlocutor-identity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Relevant Publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caffarra S, &lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Scarinci D, Mancini S, 2020 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/psyp.13527&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Who are you talking to? The role of addressee identity in utterance comprehension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wolpert M&lt;/strong&gt;, Mancini S, Caffarra S, 2017 | &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2017.01439&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Addressee Identity and Morphosyntactic Processing in Basque Allocutive Agreement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sentence processing does not rely solely on syntax and semantics &amp;ndash; pragmatics, or information that is not directly present in the linguistic message (i.e., suprasegmental), is also an essential part of language. Pragmatic information includes the interlocutor identity. Knowing who is saying something may be just as important as what is said. Some languages challenge the distinction of pragmatics as suprasegmental by directly encoding pragmatic information in the grammar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took advantage of such a linguistic feature in Basque where non-argument interlocutor information is encoded in morphosyntax, called &lt;em&gt;allocutive agreement&lt;/em&gt;. This allocutive agreement occurs in the informal register &lt;em&gt;hika&lt;/em&gt;, which is traditionally used only between the closest of friends, but has since enjoyed greater use and may be a signifier of a strong Basque identity. In allocutive agreement, there is obligatory inflectional agreement between 3rd person auxilary verbs and the gender of the addressee when the addressee is not an argument of the verb. We used conversations where allocutive verb forms were either congruent or incongruent with addressee identity, while using reaction time and ERPs to measure participants&amp;rsquo; detection of the allocutive agreement violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although other research has shown that speaker identity impacts comprehension at the earliest levels of processing, our data suggest that not all pragmatic information is so salient. Instead, knowledge about the identity of non-speaker interlocutors, including the addressee, may only influence processing at later stages. Check out the two articles linked above to find out more!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
